Guide to the Jerald Brauer Papers 1925-1999
University of Chicago Library
Brauer, Jerald. Papers
1925-1999
93.5 linear feet (184 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Jerald Brauer, historian, minister, professor, and dean. The Jerald Brauer Papers consist of ninety-three and a half linear feet and include correspondence, memos, minutes, reports, manuscripts, notes, speeches, published materials, and audio recordings. The papers document Brauer's career as a historian, professor of the history of Christianity in the Divinity School of the University of Chicago, Dean of the Federated Theological Faculties and the Divinity School, and author and editor of many scholarly books.
Information on Use
Access
All materials in Series X are restricted. Material in Subseries 1: Recent Correspondence is restricted for thirty years. Material in Subseries 2: Financial Records is restricted for fifty years. Subseries 3: Student and Faculty Records is restricted indefinitely. Subseries 4: Audio and Visual Recordings are restricted indefinitely due to the condition of the material or need for special equipment.
Biographical Note
Jerald Brauer was born in Fond du Lac, Wisconsin in 1921 to Carl L. and Anna Mae (Linde) Brauer. He attended Carthage College in Carthage, Illinois, went on to receive a B.D. from Northwestern Lutheran Theological Seminary in 1945. Brauer pursued advanced training at Union Theological Seminary in New York and earned a PhD from the University of Chicago in 1948. In 1945 Brauer married Muriel (Nelson) Brauer. The couple had two children Christopher Nelson and Marian Ruth. Brauer became an ordained minister in the United Lutheran Church of America in 1951.
Brauer began his teaching career as an instructor in church history and the history of Christianity at the Union Theological Seminary where he also served as assistant to Paul Tillich. In 1950, Brauer moved to Chicago to become Assistant Professor in History of Christianity at the University of Chicago. Associate Professor, 1954-1959. Became Professor of History of Christianity in 1959, Naomi Shenstone Donnelley professor of history of Christianity, 1969-1991, and professor emeritus in 1991.
After the establishment of the Federated Theological Faculty in 1943, Brauer served as the dean of FTF from 1955 to 1960. FTF was a formal alliance between the Divinity School at the University of Chicago, Disciples Divinity House, Meadville Theological School and the Chicago Theological Seminary. As a Lutheran, Brauer was considered by some to be an odd choice to oversee the four institutions, none of them Lutheran. When the Federation was dissolved in 1960 he became dean of the Divinity school, a position he held until 1970.
As Dean, Brauer was known for recruiting top faculty including Paul Tillich, Martin Marty, Don Browning, Clark Gilpin, and David Tracy. As the first Catholic faculty at the Divinity School, Tracy's hiring illustrated Brauer's commitment to increasing ecumenism in the Divinity School.
Brauer authored many scholarly books and articles including: Luther and the Reformation (1953) (with Jaroslav Pelikan). Protestantism in America: A Narrative History (1965), Images of Religion in America (1967), and John Nuveen: A Life of Service (1997). He also edited the collections, Reinterpretation in American Church History (1968), The Future of Religion (1966), The Lively Experiment Continued (1987), The Unrelieved Paradox: Studies in the Theology of Franz Bibfeldt (1994) (with Martin Marty), and the Westminster Dictionary of Church History (1971).
Brauer was a member of the American Society of Church History, he served as president in 1960. Brauer was the co-editor of the journal Church History from 1963 to 1998. Brauer was visiting lecturer at University of Frankfurt in 1961, and at University of Tokyo in 1966. He served as president of the board of theological education for the Lutheran Church in America from 1962 to 1968. Worked as consultant for the New York Education Department from 1969 to 1978. He was an official delegated observer for the World Council of Churches at Vatican Council II, was chairman of the Council on Religion and International Affairs from 1979-1983. He served as a trustee for Augustana College from 1964 to 1966 and at Carthage College from 1958 to 1962. He was also a visiting fellow at the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions in 1972 and 1974. Brauer was member of the board of the Carnegie Council on Ethics and International Affairs, serving as chairman between 1966 and 1983, and as chairman of the board of directors from 1979 to 1983.
Scope Note
The Jerald Brauer Papers have been arranged into ten series: Series I, Personal; Series II, Correspondence; Series III, Federated Theological Faculties, 1943-1960; Series IV, Divinity School, 1960-1985; Series V, Research and Course Notes, 1938-1975; Series VI, Sermons and Speeches, 1946-1999; Series VII, Paul Tillich (1886-1965); Series VIII, Groups and Organizations; Series IX, Writings; and Series X, Restricted.
Series I is a small series containing correspondence with friends and family, photographs, and records relating to recreational, religious, and personal business matters.
Series II contains correspondence, most of the series is made up of copies of outgoing letters. The Series is divided into eight subseries: Subseries 1, Correspondence 1936-1958; Subseries 2, Correspondence 1958-1965; Subseries 3, Correspondence 1960-1963; Subseries 4, Correspondence 1961-1965; Subseries 5, Correspondence 1964-1966; Subseries 6, Correspondence 1965-1970; Subseries 7, Correspondence 1969-1976; Subseries 8, Sidney Mead Correspondence.
Subseries 1 through 7 are divided chronologically, the overlapping periodization of some of the series follows Brauer's organizational scheme. Within each series the correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Lists of the correspondents in each folder can be found in Series II. Most of the correspondence relates to Brauer's professional life as a dean, professor, historian, mentor, and author.
Subseries 8 contains correspondence between Brauer and Sidney Mead. Mead (1904-1999) was a noted historian of American religious history and author of The Lively Experiment: The Shaping of Christianity in America (1963). The correspondence reflects both shared intellectual ties and a long friendship between the two men.
Series III, Federated Theological Faculties, consists of alphabetical subject files relating to Brauer's involvement with the Federated Theological Faculties. The formation of the FTF in 1943, formalized the relationships between the Divinity School at the University of Chicago, Disciples Divinity House, Meadville Theological School and the Chicago Theological Seminary. Brauer served as the first and only dean of FTF from 1955 until the federation was dissolved in 1960. Materials in the Series include administrative reports, minutes and correspondence, items related to the creation of the B.D. degree. The series also includes information about the defederation of FTF, organizations in which Brauer was a member, and a significant amount of material relating to the conference “Religion Faces the Atomic Age,” held in 1958.
Series IV, Divinity School, contains two subseries: Subseries 1, Subject Files and Subseries 2, Faculty Materials. Many of the files in Subseries 1 deal with the administration of the Divinity School where Brauer was dean from 1960 through 1970. Other files include material on groups, organizations, committees, and universities with ties to Brauer. The files contain a significant amount of information relating to student activism and protest on the University of Chicago Campus in the late 1960s. The visit of Cardinal Suenens to campus in 1964, is also well documented in the collection.
Subseries 2, Faculty Materials consists primarily of unpublished academic papers written by divinity school faculty arranged alphabetically within the series.
Series V, Research and Course Notes, contains two subseries: Subseries 1, Dissertation Notes and Drafts and Subseries 2, Research Documents and Notes. Subseries I contains notes, draft chapters, and correspondence relating to Brauer's dissertation, “Francis Rous, Puritan Mystic, 1579-1659: An Introduction to the Study of the Mystical Element in Puritanism,” which he completed in 1949 at the University of Chicago.
Subseries 2, Documents and Notes, also contains materials relating to Brauer's research in religious history, particularly the history of Puritanism, revivalism, and mysticism. The series also includes notes for courses taken by Brauer as a graduate student in the Divinity School, notes and syllabi for classes given by Brauer, and some syllabi for classes given by other faculty members.
Series VI, Sermons and Speeches, contains draft copies of sermons and speeches given by Brauer. They include commencement addresses, memorials, and academic lectures.
Series VII contains personal and professional correspondence between Brauer, Paul Tillich, and Hannah Tillich as well as secondary materials relating to Tillich including published essays, reviews, and clippings. The Series also includes draft copies of Paul Tillich's diaries later published as My Travel Diary, 1936: Between Two Worlds (1970). Brauer edited the diary for publication and provided an introduction.
Series VIII documents Brauer's involvement with various academic, religious and civic groups. The Series is divided into eight subseries: 1. Council on Religion and International Affairs, 2. American Society for Church History, 3. National Council of Churches of Christ, 4. Center for the Study of Religious Institutions, 5. Board of Theological Education, 6. International House of the University of Chicago. Subseries 8 includes materials related to Brauer's work as a consultant for New York State. As a consultant, Brauer investigated denominational colleges and universities to determine whether they met eligibility criteria for state financial aid under the Bundy Act.
Subseries 1, Council on Religion and International Affairs (CRIA), documents Brauer's involvement with the organization. CRIA (now know as the Carnegie Council on Ethics and International Affairs) was founded in 1914 by Andrew Carnegie with a mission to promote world peace through research and education in ethics and international affairs. The series contains reports and proposals as well as administrative correspondence and minutes.
Subseries 2, American Society for Church History, contains materials relating to the American Society of Church History as well as it's journal Church History. The Society was founded in 1888 to promote scholarly exploration in the history of religion. Brauer was a member of the Society throughout his academic career and served as president in 1960. From 1963 to 1998, Brauer was also co-editor of Church History. The series consists primarily of reports and correspondence relating to Church History.
Subseries 3, National Council of Churches of Christ includes reports and correspondence relating to the National Council of Churches, a Protestant ecumenical organization formed in 1950. The series contains reports, correspondence, and miscellaneous materials about the organization.
Subseries 4, Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (CSDI) contains material about Brauer's participation in the organization. CSDI began in 1954 as the Fund for the Republic, a group founded by former University of Chicago president Robert Maynard Hutchins. The Center began in response to concerns about abuses of civil liberties in the United States. In subsequent decades the CSDI went on to examine a variety of contemporary social issues. Brauer was a visiting fellow at the CSDI in 1972 and again in 1974. The subseries includes papers given at the center by Brauer and others, as well as Brauer's notes and correspondence.
Subseries 5, Board for Theological Education. BTE was an organization designed to oversee the development of Lutheran theological seminaries in the United States and more broadly, the overall development of postsecondary theological and religious training in the United States. BTE was affiliated with the United Lutheran Church in America. The series is made up primarily of administrative materials, correspondence, reports, and minutes.
Subseries 6, International House, contains materials relating to International House of Chicago. International House was found by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in 1932 with a mission to promote cross-cultural understanding and friendship among students and scholars. The series contains correspondence, administrative materials related to Brauer's service on the International House board, and information about a Swedish International House.
Subseries 7, New York State Consultations, Bundy Funds, includes materials from Brauer's work as a consultant for the New York Education Department between 1969 and 1978. New York State passed the Bundy Act in 1968 to provide financial assistance to independent colleges. Brauer's work for the state involved examining the religious teaching and institutional culture at private denominational colleges to ascertain whether they met criteria that prohibited sectarian teaching at schools receiving Bundy monies. The subseries includes Brauer's reports about schools, supplementary materials, and correspondence.
Series IX: Writings, is made up of published and unpublished work by Brauer and others. The collection also includes a small amount of correspondence about various book projects. The series includes two subseries, 1. Book Projects and Publishers and 2. Articles and Off-prints. Subseries 1 contains drafts and correspondence about The Chicago School Reader, The Westminster Dictionary of Church History, John Nuveen: A Life in Service, and The Lively Experiment Continued, The Chicago Encyclopedia of Religion, Protestantism in America
Subseries 2, contains copies of published articles and off-prints written by Brauer and others.
Series X contains restricted materials. All materials in Series X are restricted.
Material in Subseries 1: Recent Correspondence is restricted for thirty years.
Material in Subseries 2: Financial Records is restricted for fifty years. Subseries
3: Student and Faculty Records is restricted indefinitely. Subseries 4: Audio and
Visual Recordings are restricted indefinitely due to the condition of the material or
need for special equipment.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Brauer, Jerald C.; Arendt, Hannah; Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989; Eliade, Mircea 1907-1986; Gilkey, Langdon Brown, 1919-; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899; Kimpton, Lawrence Alpheus, 1910-; Kitagawa, Joseph Mitsuo, 1915-; Levi, Edward Hirsch, 1911-; Marty, Martin E., 1928; Mead, Sidney M.; Nuveen, John, 1896-; Pelikan, Jaroslav Jan, 1923-; Sittler, Joseph; Suenens, Leon Joseph, 1904-; Tillich, Hannah; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965; Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions; Chicago Theological Seminary; Council on Religion and International Affairs; University of Chicago. International House; McCormick Theological Seminary; Meadville Theological School; University of Chicago. Divinity School; University of Chicago-Faculty; University of Chicago. Federated Theological Faculties; Ecumenism; Christianity -- History; Student Protest
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal, 1938-1994
  Series I is a small series containing correspondence with friends and family, photographs, and records relating to recreational, religious, and personal business matters.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, Seeberger, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, Christopher Brauer, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes of the Semitic Club/Near East Club, 1903-1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Japan Schedule, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Haroutunian Memorial, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Arrangements for England Trip, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, "Reminiscences," 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - C.V., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, Personal, 1953-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Illinois Synod Documents, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal Business Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1970-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Retirement Colloquium Notes, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Johnson Wax Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - President Harper Notes, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Signature Styles, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1958 (see Oversize BOX 184, Folder 1) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1940-1970
  Series II contains incoming and outgoing correspondence from 1940 to 1970. Series II is divided into eight subseries: 1. Correspondence, 1936-1958, 2. Correspondence 1958-1965, 3. Correspondence 1960-1963, 4. Correspondence, 1961-1965, 5. Correspondence, 1964-1966, 6. Correspondence 1965-1970, 7. Correspondence, 1969-1976, and 8. These series preserve Brauer's own organizational scheme.
  Subseries 1 through 7 are divided chronologically, the overlapping periodization of some of the series follows Brauer's organizational scheme. Within each series the correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Lists of the correspondents in each folder can be found in Series II. Most of the correspondence relates to Brauer's professional life as a dean, professor, historian, mentor, and author
  Subseries 8 contains correspondence between Brauer and Sidney Mead. Mead (1904-1999) was a noted historian of American religious history and author of The Lively Experiment: The Shaping of Christianity in America (1963). The correspondence reflects both shared intellectual ties and a long friendship between the two men.
  Additional personal correspondence can be found in Series I. Series VII contains additional correspondence with and about theologian Paul Tillich. Additional restricted correspondence appears in Series X.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, 1936-1958
    - Shirley Jackson Case Correspondence, 1939-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Edgar Goodspeed Correspondence, 1943-1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Shailer Matthews Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Herbert Phillips Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ira Price Correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - J.M. Powis Smith Correspondence, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - W.W. Sweet Correspondence, 1936-1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Clyde Votaw, 1938-1946 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - H.L. Willett Correspondence, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - A-E, Bob Allen W. Aubrey Alsobrook Robert Anderson Robert Asmuth George Avent Bachmann, Charles Barkwell, Gordon Harold Bernhard Howard Bechtolt Harold Belgum Bingham, William Bittner, Madison W.B. Blakemore Bosley, Harold Brauer, Mrs. Howard Buckles, Joe Cabaniss, Allen Carney, Frederick Carter, John Paul Charles, Carroll Christenson, Evelyn Clark, A. Bryan Coburn, Hayward Coffin, Henry Connelly, John Cooke, John Crist, George Damrel, Mary Dirks, J. Edward Ecklund, Diane Eastman, Fred (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - F-L, Fildey, Harold Findley, Cecil Fischer, Robert Flack, E.E. Funk, Paul Fry, Franklin Gaus, John Gehring, P. Gessert, Robert Giere, Arthur Gillander, Alexander Glossop, Ron Goeser, Robert Granrud, Carl Gregory, Basil Gruman, Larry Haker, Carl Halvorson, H.O. Hawley, William Hiltner, Seward Hogue, Harland Howard, Webb Hudson, Winthrop Hunt, Myron Hutchins, Francis (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - M-P, McCaul, Robert McCracken, Robert McGiffert, A.C. McNulty, Rosemary McNutt, E.S. Mangum, John Mattson, Karl E. Meacham, Paul Mead, Sidney Miller, Alan Moquin, Wayne Nielsen, Ernest Norwood, Fred Nuveen, John Oberholzer, Emil Peck, Isabelle Petersen, Alvin Price, John M. Pruter, Hugo (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - R-Z, Raun, James Ritter, Jack Roberts, Walter Ross, Robert Schneider, Carl Setzer, Roy Shinn, Roger Siktberg, William Smith, Chad Sovik, Ansgar Sommerfeld, John Speaker, Louis Stamps, Sarah Ann Stilwell, Arnold Storr, Richard Strozier, Robert Stuart, Marjorie Swartz, Merlin Thordarson, Thorir Tillich, Paul Ungerer, Billy Grace Wagoner, Walter Welborn, E. P. Westberg, Granger Wheatly, Robert Wickey, Gould Williams, Daniel Williams, Mentor Willoughby, Harold Wimmer, Charles R. Wright, Elizabeth Wynne, Marjorie Yeagy, Arthur Yoder, Donald Ziegenfus, James (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence, 1958-1965
    - Correspondence, A-B, Adams, James L. Akers, Milburn Albaugh, Gaylord Albert, Harold Allin, J. Bryan Altizer, Thomas J. J. Anderson, A. Edwin Anderson, Bernhard Anderson, George Anderson, Stuart LeRoy Arnott, Robert J. Averill, Lloyd J. Bachman, E. Theodore Ballard, John Barbour, Ian G. Barkwell, Gordon Barrett, Evangeline Barth, Markus Beadle, George W. Bedikian, A.A. Beker, J. Christiaan Bell, Cyril N. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Ben-Butts, Benedict, Wilbur D. Bennett, John C. Bens, Ernst Berggren, Paul Bertram, Robert Beth, Karl Bethany Theological Seminary Beto, George Blaes, Arnold Blake, Eugene Blizzard, Samuel W. Bloesch, Donald Bock, Paul Bohmfalk, Erwin Bohr, Ronald Boisen, Anton Bordon, Stanley P. Bosley, Harold Boyd, T. Braeman, John Brandon, George Bray, Allen F. Bremer, David H. Brewster, William Brigham, John W. Brown, Kenneth Brune, Audrey Buttrick, David Buttrick, George Butts, T. L. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - C, Cadbury, Henry Cannon, William R. Carty, James W. Clark, William H. Cahill, Arthur Cleveland, Philip Jerome Clinard, Gordon Cohen Arthur Cole, J. Preston Cole, Myron Colston, Lowell G. Colwell, Ernest Cadman (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Coo-Cu, Cooke, Bernard J. Corey, Kendall Coop, Frank D. Cornell, William A. Cotton, Albert F. Creel, Dana Crowson, George Crummey, D. Clifford Counselbaum, A.B. Crary, Calvert Cressman, Harry Crowson, George Cull, David J. Cully, Kendig Brubaker Curtis, C.N. Cutshall, E. Guy (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - D-E, Daniel, Irene B. Davidson, Glen W. Davis, Guy M. Deeter, Emily F. Deisher, Mary Sue DeVeny, Dean R. DeWitt, Robert L. Dietz, Reginald Dillenberger, John Dillman, David Dotson, Earl Douglass, Edward V. Dobyns, Lester Dorn, William Dunn, Ruth Durgin, Lawrence Dyck, Cornelius Eastman, Fred Ebersole, Mark C. Eklund, Emmet Elliott, Patrick Ellis, John Tracy English, Darrell D. Erling, Bernhard Esler, David Evans, Joseph P. Exman, Eugene Evjen, Victor H. Fackre, Gabriel Evans, David B. Eusden, John (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - F, Fair, Harold Fargo, Jerry Fate, Russell Feilding, Charles Ferm, Robert L. Fevold, Eugene Filas, Francis Filbey, Emery T. Finnegan, Terence Fischer, Bob Fitzpatrick, T.M. Fixler, Michael Flack, E.E. Flottorp, Haakon Foster, A. Durwood Freiberg, Arthur Freeman, George Fry, Franklin D. Friess, Horace Fulton, Everett Funk, Paul William Funkay, William J. Fussler, Herman H. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - G, Gale, Horace Lincicome, Arthur Gamble, Connolly Garhart, John D. Gaus, John E. Geanakoplos, Deno Gibbs, Mark Gibson, Boyd Gibson, R.J. Gieseman, A. Wayne Gilkey, Langdon Gilkey, James Gordon Gill, Theodore Gilpatric, Chadbourne Ginzberg, Eli Goodman, Howard Gordh, George Graf, Fred Graham, George A. Grant, Robert M. Grady, Albert Gross, Jefferey T. Guillemin, J. Duchesne Gustafson, C.V. (Box 4, Folder 7)